Without the first issue, there's not much we can do.
創刊号がないと 話にならんぞ
That's true.
そうですね
I'd feel a bit more confident about this investigation if you asked Satoshi and Ibara as well.
里志と伊原でも加われば 心強いんだがな
Well, I'd prefer...
いえ あの それは
Even if we can't solve the mystery, it'll be ancient history soon enough.
まあ 謎が解けなかったとしても
いつかお前の中で時効になっていくのかもな
History?
時効に
分かりました
All right.
福部さんと摩耶花さんにもお願いしてみましょう
I'll ask Fukube and Mayaka for their assistance.
I can't stop thinking about it!
私 気になります
四十五年前 叔父に何が起きたのか
Please help me find out what happened to my uncle 45 years ago!
皆さん よろしくお願いします
千反田のおじさんがね
Your uncle, huh?
そんなことがあったんだ
I had no idea.
英雄譚の秘話
That epic from the past, full of heroism and hidden tragedy...
それを四十五年後の後輩が解くか
To think, we might uncover the truth 45 years later.
In fact, I was just researching that period myself.
ちょうどその時期のことを調べてたんだ
Were you? Well, this picture makes me curious as well.
そうね この絵も気になるし
If there's some meaning to it, I'd also like to find out what it is.
由来があるなら 私も知りたい
何だかわくわくするね
Pretty exciting, huh?
うまくすれば 文集のネタになるかもな
You know, if we do this right, it could be the topic of this year's anthology.
Let's make this investigation into an official club activity.
古典部の活動として 気の済むように調べればいい
And thus, investigating the past has become the utmost priority for all Classics Club members.
こうして 古典部の過去を探ることが
全古典部員の最優先事項と相成った
Bored, sitting on the windowsill,
退屈な窓辺に吹き込む風に
I frown at the wind to hide my awkwardness
顔を顰めたのは照れくさ　その裏返し
Hyouka
KamiGami
@ 湮·Molly／小然·酸菜／喵儿·小冷／时末·竭力而为
I nod uncertainly as I shape
曖昧に頷く掌の今日
the future in my hands feeling mighty
描いてる自分は少し大袈裟で
I feel that the wind is bringing change
何かが変わりそうな気がしているよ
I guess that's your fault for calling out to my heart
心に呼びかける君のせいだね
The cloudy sky tells a tale of what's to come
曇り空覗いた予感
Spread our wings with more courage than ever before
手を伸ばそう　いつよりも力強い勇気で
Light and dark are still vague in the distance
光も影もまだ遠くで
but still we want to know the reason behind kindness
それでも僕らは優しさの理由が知りたい
No one so far has ever reached
今は誰の名前でもない
the shining distance far beyond
輝きの彼方へ
Let's get there before the past takes it all
全部過去になる前に見つけに行こう
Past Days of the Classics Club and Its Glory
绽放荣光的古籍研究社之过往
ごっめーん
Sorry, honey! Wait long?
待ったー？
何だよ 奉太郎
What's wrong with you, Houtarou?
喧しい お前には羞恥心がないのか
Shut up! Have you no shame?
で 資料は準備できたのか
So, did you manage to get some documents together?
How about you? Did you come up with a good topic?
奉太郎こそどうだい いいネタはあったかい
Well... Sort of.
まあな
なら 仮説のほうも期待できそうだね
I'm looking forward to hearing your theory as to what happened.
Crap. Was I supposed to prepare a theory, too?
しまった そんな話もあったっけか
Let's get going, then.
よし じゃ行こうか
The Chitanda family's full of rich farmers, so their Kamiyama mansion is top class!
豪農千反田家のお屋敷は神山市でトップクラスだよ
お前 楽しそうだな
Aren't you enjoying yourself?
そりゃサイクリングは楽しいさ
Of course I am! I love cycling!
風を切って 自分の脚力で突っ走っていく この
Going head-on against the wind with nothing but the power of my legs! And—
違う
That's not it. Your high school life in general.
お前の高校生活全般がだ
ああ バラ色の話ね
Ah, that "colorful" business, right?
僕はね 周りがどうあれ基本属性がバラ色なんだよ
You could say that most people around me live colorful lives as well.
More like, neon bright.
ショッピングピンクだろ むしろ
そいつはいい
I guess. But you're pretty dull by comparison.
それでいくなら 奉太郎は灰色だね
そいつは前にも聞いた
Yeah, I've heard that one before.
そうだっけ
Oh, right. I don't look down on you for that, though.
でも僕は別に奉太郎を貶めるつもりはないよ
僕は基本属性がショッピングピンクだからね
I'm neon bright by nature,
誰かが僕をバラ色に染めようとしても駄目さ
so just being "colorful" doesn't really work for me.
染まってあげない
意外と染まってないか
You haven't settled for that already?
Not at all.
それはないね
What was that, Houtarou?
なんだい 奉太郎
You're asking because you see how busy I am with the Council and the Handicrafts Club?
僕が総務員や手芸部で忙しくしてるから そんなこと言うのかい
違うのか
Am I wrong?
違うよ
You are.
Whatever I do, I'll always be me.
何をしていたって僕は僕だからね
染まってるわけじゃない
I won't tone myself down to fit in.
僕が貶める時には
If I looked down on you, instead of "dull" I'd say you had no personality at all.
君は無色だって言うよ
僕はお前に好かれたいとは思ってない
I can live without your love.
I'm sure you can.
違いないや
Anyway, how did your midterms go?
そう言えば 奉太郎 中間テストはどうだった
どれも平均点だった
Average marks on every one.
さすが灰色の奉太郎だね
Just what I'd expect from Your Dullness.
見えてきたよ
Look, over there.
あれが千反田邸さ
That's the Chitanda mansion.
どうだい 見事なもんだろ
What do you think? Isn't it amazing?
Let's go. The girls will be waiting.
行こう 千反田たちが待ってる
そうだね  奉太郎
That's true.
Houtarou,
何か使用人が出迎えてくれそうじゃないか
aren't you expecting servants to show up and greet us?
いらっしゃい
Welcome! Come in. We've been waiting for you.
お待ちしていました
お邪魔します
Excuse us.
どうぞ こちらです
Please, this way.
お好きな所に座ってください
Just sit down wherever you like.
遅かったわね
You sure took your time.
遅れてはいない
But we're not late.
床の間を背負うのがこれほども似合わない男も珍しい
I've never seen someone look so out of place in a room.
さて 始めましょうか 検討会
Then, shall we begin the investigation meeting?
はーい
Yeah!
Sure!
Okay.
今日は 四十五年前に古典部に起きた事件について 考えたいと思います
Today, I'd like to focus on what happened in the Classics Club 45 years ago.
If we can find out the truth,
真相にたどり着いたら
I'd like to include it in this year's anthology.
今年の古典部の文集に載せたいと思います
先ず資料の配布と報告
Firstly, the gathered data and reports.
次にそれについての質問
Then, any questions regarding them.
次に報告者の仮説
Following that, your theories.
And finally, I'd like to closely evaluate those theories.
最後に仮説の検討という順で進めたいと思います
She's a good chairman.
なかなかの名司会
では 最初の報告を
Well then, the first report...
あれ ええと 誰からにしたらいいんでしょう
Who should we start from?
でもないか
...or not.
Whatever. Chitanda, you start.
誰でもいいだろ
千反田 お前からやれ
そうですね
I guess. Then let's go around from me in clockwise order.
じゃ 私から時計回りにしましょうか
I investigated the second issue of Hyouka itself.
私が調べたのは氷菓そのものです
The only part with any mention of what happened 45 years ago is the introduction.
四十五年前のことに触れていたのはこの序文だけでした
I've summarized the important facts on the second sheet.
そこから読み取れる事実を二枚目にまとめました
2.) 45 years ago he was a hero, 44 years ago he was a legend
3.) He was a "quiet fighter" and a "kind hero"
4) He coined the name "Hyouka"
5.) There was a sacrifice in the fight (was it my uncle?)
1) Sekitani has left us (but who did he leave?)
The first one is about my uncle, Sekitani Jun.
まず一ですね
先輩は 私の叔父 関谷純を指します
He left Kamiyama High without graduating,
叔父は神山高校を中退していまして
最終学歴は中卒でした
so the highest level of education he completed was middle school.
2.) 45 years ago he was a hero, 44 years ago he was a legend
次に二ですが
I think the second one refers to how stories become exaggerated over time.
これは時間経過によって話が大げさになるということだと思います
2.) 45 years ago he was a hero, 44 years ago he was a legend
3.) He was a "quiet fighter" and a "kind hero"
4) He coined the name "Hyouka"
5.) There was a sacrifice in the fight (was it my uncle?)
1) Sekitani has left us (but who did he leave?)
三と五は繋がりますね
The third and fifth are connected.
静かで優しい先輩は闘士になった後 英雄になり
He was quiet and kind, and he first became a fighter, then a hero.
最後は 犠牲になっています
And in the end...
A sacrifice.
4) He coined the name "Hyouka"
四は気になりますけど 今回は外しましょう
The fourth is quite interesting, but let's put it aside for now.
以上が報告になります
That's the end of my report.
質問はありますか
Do you have any questions?
あのさ あれは英雄譚などでは決してなかったってとこをは抜かしたのはなんで
epic
Why did you ignore the part that says, "it was nothing even close to an epic"?
そこは書き手の心象ですから
Because that's the writer's own interpretation.
そんな格好いいものじゃなくて もっと泥臭い戦いだったって意味かもね
Maybe they meant that it wasn't all so glorious, but more of a dirty fight.
なるほど
I see.
では 仮説を発表しますね
Now for my hypothesis:
My uncle confronted something, and as a result he had to leave the school.
叔父は何かと争い
その結果学校から去ったと考えられます
ここで一つ
One other thing.
今挙げた五つ以外の要素を考えてみました
I considered a few other things in addition to those five points.
もう一年になるという部分です
For instance, this part about how "one year has passed."
叔父が退学したのはやはり「カンヤ祭」の時期ですね
My uncle left the school around the time of the Kan'ya fair.
話が逸れますが
As a side note,
別の友人から 去年文化祭で事件があったと聞きました
I heard from a friend of mine who studies at another school
that there was an incident at last year's fair.
文化祭荒らしだね
I've heard of those troublemakers.
売り子が恐喝されて 売り上げが消えたとか
There are people who like to threaten the sellers, and make off with their profits.
いわゆる不良と呼ばれる方は どんな時代にもいたと思います
I think there are always people like that at fairs.
その年の「カンヤ祭」は不幸にもそのような人たちの標となったため
Perhaps that year my uncle was unfortunate enough to be targeted,
叔父は暴力で抵抗して 英雄になったのではないでしょうか
and he tried to resist by force.
Could that be how he became a hero?
責任を取って退学した叔父を惜しんだ後輩がこの文を残したんだと思います
He took responsibility and left the school,
and the students he left behind wrote this.
It couldn't be that.
却下だな
Yeah, couldn't be.
却下だね
駄目ですか 理由を教えてください
It's no good?
Please, tell me why!
千反田 お前が最初に文集の話をした時
Chitanda,
when you first suggested making an anthology, do you remember what I wanted to do instead?
俺が何って言って反対したか覚えてるか
Um... A stall, right?
えっと 模擬店ですね
そうだ
That's it. But you said that stalls are traditionally disallowed.
だが お前は模擬店は伝統的に禁止されていると言ったな
金が動かないカンヤ祭には 文化祭荒らしも寄ってこないだろ
There's not much money to be made at the Kan'ya Fair,
so why would troublemakers turn up?
お金が絡まなくても寄ってくる方はいると思います
There are probably some who'd turn up even without the promise of money.
Are you even trying, Houtarou?
情けないな 奉太郎は
Oh? I'm sure we'd all love to hear what you think.
じゃ お前の意見を聞かせてもらおうか
文化祭荒らしは四十五年前だと不思議も不思議
First of all, believe it or not, there were no such troublemakers 45 years ago.
まず起こらなかったんだよ
何で
Why?
If I mention the 1960s, what comes to mind?
1960年代って言えば 何か思い出さないかい
東京 国会議事堂
Tokyo... The National Diet Building...
プラカード デモ
Placards... Demonstrations...
What are you talking about, Satoshi?
里志 何の話をしてるんだ
学生運動だよ
The student movement.
いいかい
The kind of school violence that Chitanda mentioned was hardly present in the 1960s.
千反田さんが言った類の校内暴力は
1960年代にはまだほとんど見られないんだ
喧嘩する相手が教師や学校じゃなくて 国家とか体制っていう時代だからね
They didn't fight the schools or their teachers,
they fought the state and the system.
見てきたようなことを言うな
You talk as if you were there.
言ったろ
Like I said, I did some research into that period.
その時期のこと調べてるって
That's right. I forgot to consider the political climate of that time.
確かに 時代性というのは盲点でしたね
チ―ちゃん ごめん
I'm sorry, Chi!
どうしたんですか 突然
Why are you apologizing?
私の資料だと ちーちゃんの説が成り立たないの
The data I gathered doesn't fit your theory.
次が私の番だから どこまで話したらいいか分かんなくて
I'm next, so I don't really know how much detail I should go into...
おのれ伊原
Damn Ibara and her pointless chatter...
無駄な話をさせやがって
では 私の説を一時取り下げにしますので
Then, let's put my theory aside for now.
摩耶花さんの説を聞かせてください
How about yours, Mayaka?
Is that okay?
それでいいですか
はーい
Yeah.
足が痺れた
My legs are numb.
This mansion is really huge.
それにしても広いお屋敷だね
庭に池があったりするのかい
Do you have a pond in your garden?
ありますよ
Yes.
本当に ぜひ見てみたいな
Really? Can I see?
私も見たい
Me too!
では 続きは場所を変えましょうか
Okay, time for a change of scene!
The weather is just perfect on the veranda.
縁側はとっても気持ちがいいんですよ
池 ね
A pond, huh?
芒种
有芒之种谷可稼种矣
Awn Grain
The time when awns bear seeds.
Hyouka
これ 図書室で見つけた「団結と祝砲」一号って本のコピーなの
I found this in the library.
It's the first issue of Salute and Solidarity.
二号以降は見つからなかったわ
I couldn't find any later ones, though.
It's from 44 years ago, the same as Chi's.
発行はちーちゃんのと同じ 四十四年前ね
Salute
and
Solidarity
Therefore we are the masses, and as such we
are anti-bureaucratic and independent. We would
never yield to the aggression of the reactionaries.
One needs only consider the class war of last
June, when under the heroic leadership of the
Classics Club's president Sekitani Jun, our daring
activism broke the ranks of the spineless
authoritarians, and they fled in unsightly shame.
我々の果敢なる実行主義ときたか
"Our daring activism"? Sounds like the '60s all right.
時代がかってるな
じゃ 始めるね
Let's start from the beginning. "We" referred to the students,
We
先ず「我々」が生徒を指して
while the "reactionaries" and the "authoritarians" were the teachers.
Reactionaires
Authoritarians
反動勢力と権力主義者の先生を指しているとするね
Reactionaires
Authoritarians
There was a "class war" during June of the previous year,
June
前の年の六月に闘争があって
and it was led by none other than the Classics Club's president, Sekitani Jun.
その指導をしたのが古典部の部長 関谷純って人だった
Activism
で 実行主義っていうのをやって 先生たちを困らせた
Furthermore, their activism caused trouble for the teachers.
Activism
Oh, so that word means "class war" and not just "fight", huh?
これ「斗争」じゃなくて「闘争」と読むのか
この「団結と祝砲」って 何だかうさんくさいね
This whole Salute and Solidarity thing is pretty fishy.
うさんくさい
Fishy?
この期日を疑ってるわけじゃないよ
I'm not saying that this document is fake,
大学とかの華々しい運動に憧れた人が書いたのかなと思って
just that it was written by someone immersed in the student movement.
So what?
で それがどうかしたのか
Nothing. Just thinking out loud.
いいや 独り言さ
Sorry, Chitanda.
ごめん 千反田さん
では ほかに質問はありませんか
Any other questions?
Then, here's my theory.
じゃ 私の仮説ね
まずちーちゃん説の否定
I refute Chi's hypothesis.
「団結と祝砲」だと 事件が起こったのは六月になるのよね
According to Salute and Solidarity, the incident was in June.
退学しなけいけないような実行
If it was bad enough that he had to leave the school, violence must have been involved.
思いつくのは暴力よね
つまり関谷純に率いられた人たちは
So, the students led by Sekitani Jun went like this,
先生たちをこう
ポカリとやっちゃった
and gave the teachers a good whacking.
We don't know if they actually beat the teachers,
実際に殴ったかは分かんないけど
四十五年前 生徒の自主性が損なわれる何かがあって
but 45 years ago something threatened the autonomy of the students, and they resisted.
それに反発したんじゃないかな
My uncle...
伯父がですか
摩耶花の言いたいことはなんとなくわかるけど
I see what you're getting at, Mayaka, but still...
どういうこと？
What do you mean?
摩耶花の説は先生からの抑圧に対抗して
Your point is that the students resisted the teachers' oppression with violence.
生徒が暴力を働いたってことだよね
うん そうかな
Yeah.
Your theory is too abstract.
お前の説は抽象的すぎる
もっともこれ以上は読み取りようもないが
We can't learn anything more from it.
確かに具体的かって言われるとそうじゃないけど
Sure, it's objective, but is it controversial?
矛盾はあった？
あるね
Yes.
Hyouka
Salute and Solidarity
If we believe both Hyouka and Salute and Solidarity,
「氷菓」も「団結と祝砲」も信じると
then the incident happened in June, but he wasn't expelled until October.
事件は六月 退学は文化祭のある十月だ
Incident
June
Expelled
October
暴力行為による処罰なら 事件のすぐあとに退学させるはずだろ？
If he was to be punished for a violent incident, he would've been expelled right after, in June.
July August September
June
October
Incident
Expelled
June
October
Incident
Expelled
June
October
Incident
Expelled
June
October
Incident
Expelled
June
October
Incident
Expelled
June
July August September
Incident
October
Expelled
そうかな
That's true.
Yeah, I'm wondering about that four-month difference as well.
私もこの四ヶ月のズレは気になります
It said a year had passed as of the fair, so he'd probably been expelled in October.
文化祭を以ってもう一年って言ってるんだし
退学は十月なんじゃないかな
You sure like to nitpick, don't you?
みんな細かい性格してるね
方向性はいい線行ってると思うよ
I think we're heading in the right direction, though.
そうですね
That's right.
じゃあ 私の順番はこれで終わりでいいの？
I guess that's it for me, then.
Yes, thank you. Then, next up is—
はい ありがとうございます
では 次は…
Sorry. I got kinda hungry.
ごめん なんかお腹減っちゃって
But you've been nibbling sweets all the time!
もう お菓子いっぱい食べたでしょう？
いや
おにぎりでよければ 作れますよ
If you're okay with rice balls, I'll make lunch.
皆さんもどうですか
Is that all right with everyone?
ちーちゃん 何か手伝おうか
Chi, is there anything we can help with?
Don't worry about it.
いえ 大丈夫ですよ
Really?
そう
はい
Yeah.
手作りだよ
A handmade lunch!
嬉しそうだな
I see you're overjoyed.
福ちゃん これって
Fuku, this...
摩耶花 ごめん
Mayaka, I'm sorry!
僕の資料だと 摩耶花の説が部分否定されるんだ
My data sort of conflicts with yours.
言い忘れてたよ
I forgot to mention it before.
Oh, really?
そうなの
これは「神高月報」か
Is this the Kami High Monthly?
そういえば 遠垣内が五百号近いと言ってたな
Right, Tougaito did say they were nearing the 500th issue.
そのとおり
That's right!
僕が調べたのは壁新聞部が発行してる神高月報のバックナンバー
I went through the older issues of the Kami High Monthly.
四十五年前の事件に触れているのはこれくらいしかなかったよ
This was the only one that mentioned what happened 45 years ago.
で 要約が二枚目
The second sheet contains my summary.
- There was no violence involved.
- It influenced the whole school.
- There was a united group ("us") at the center.
- They used non-violent disobedience.
最初と最後は同じことだろうね
The first and the last point say the same thing.
- There was no violence involved.
- It influenced the whole school.
- There was a united group ("us") at the center.
- They used non-violent disobedience.
- There was no violence involved.
- It influenced the whole school.
- There was a united group ("us") at the center.
- They used non-violent disobedience.
- There was no violence involved.
- It influenced the whole school.
- There was a united group ("us") at the center.
- They used non-violent disobedience.
事件で暴力は振るわれなかったんだから 摩耶花の説は軌道修正
There was no violence involved,
which derails Mayaka's theory.
Furthermore, if the usage of "us" refers to the whole school,
あとは「全学」 つまり全校生徒が「我々」なら
whole school         "us"
that means that the whole student body was involved in the incident.
事件には生徒全体が関わったことになるし
Or failing that, it was at least led by someone supported by the whole student body.
そうじゃない場合は 全校生徒の指示を得た誰かが関与したことになる
お待たせしました
Here you go.
ありがとう ちーちゃん
Thanks, Chi.
いえ
No problem.
I made some with plum, kelp, and leaf mustard filling.
梅と昆布と高菜があります
どうぞ召し上がってください
Please, help yourselves.
いただきまーす
Thanks!
What's wrong?
どうしたの？
Nothing.
べつに
うまい
This is good!
美味しい
It's great!
このお米って 千反田さんの家で作ってるの？
Do you grow this rice yourselves?
そうなんです
Yes.
あ 質問があればどうぞ
If you have any questions, go ahead.
この伝説的な運動は関谷純が退学した事件で間違いないのか
Are you sure this "legendary movement" was the same one Sekitani Jun was involved in?
このコピーだけじゃどうにも怪しいが
This paper alone doesn't really explain that.
さあね 証拠はない
Who knows? I've got no proof.
さあねって それじゃ資料にならんだろ
"Who knows?"
That's not very convincing.
I guess.
そうかな やっぱり
There's indirect proof, though.
でもさ 間接的な証拠ならあるよ
Sekitani Jun incident
If the Sekitani incident and this "legendary movement" were separate,
関谷純の事件と伝説的な運動が違うなら
Sekitani Jun incident
Legendary movement
ふたつのうち こっちが伝説的な運動だっていう一文があるんじゃない？
they'd refer to this "legendary movement" in more specific terms.
That's it! Just what I wanted to say!
そうそう それが言いたかったんだ
You're good, Mayaka!
さすが摩耶花だね
Next, let's hear your theory, please.
では 仮説をお願いします
ああ 仮説ね
My theory, huh?
どうしたんですか
What's wrong?
I'm sorry, Chitanda, but I can't come up with a theory on my own.
千反田さん わるいけど仮説は立たないよ
たったこれだけじゃ伊原説を修正するのが関の山だね
The most I can do is reconcile Ibara's theory with the new facts.
And as you know,
それに データベースは結論を出せないんだ
a database can't draw conclusions.
言うと思った
I knew he'd say that.
さあて
Now,
Thank you.
It's okay.
どうするか
what should I do...
では折木さん お願いします
Oreki, please begin.
奉太郎 これってもしかして
Houtarou, is this what I think it is?
Kamiyama High School: Fifty Years of History?
神山高校五十年の歩みですか
公的記録に何か載ってないかと思ってなあ
I suspected some of the details might not have been kept in public records.
But looking at it again, there's nothing really worthy of mention.
しかし 改めて見ると語るべき内容は何もないな
And I have no theory. What now?
仮説もないし さてどうするか
どうしたの？ 奉太郎
What's wrong, Houtarou?
Did you forget the procedure?
ちょっと 進め方忘れちゃったの？
まず 要約からですが
Start from the summary, please.
そもそも これはやらなければいけないことなのか
Do I really have to do this?
Houtarou!
奉太郎？
Oreki!
折木？
折木さん？
Oreki?
Damn it...
もういい
流すか
Just let it go.
どうしたの？
What's wrong?
I forgot that we're drying shiitake mushrooms!
忘れていました シイタケを干していたんです
I need to take them in right away!
急いで取り込まないと
Do you need a hand?
一人で大丈夫？
ええ 大丈夫です
I'll be fine.
Chitanda!
千反田
Yes?
はい？
すまん ちょっと手洗いを借りていいか
Sorry, could I use the bathroom?
あ はい
Sure. Just go straight down that corridor.
ここを出て まっすぐ進んだところですので
緊張でもしたのかい
Suffering from page fright?
まっすぐ まっすぐ
Straight...
Wait, where am I?
迷った
こんなに調べてたのか
She did this much research, huh?
少しは頭を使ってみるか
I guess I could put my head to use for once.
四十五年前
45 years ago...
関谷純に起こった出来事
What happened to Sekitani Jun?
四つの資料
Four sources,
それらを結ぶものは
connected by...
Think.
考えろ
学生運動
The student movement... A violent incident... The time before he was expelled...
暴力行為
退学時期のズレ
四十五年前
45 years ago... Sekitani Jun...
関谷純
You sure took your time.
随分長かったね
わるかったな たしか俺の発表の番だったな
Sorry about that.
It's my turn, isn't it?
Sorry. I didn't prepare a theory,
すまんが 仮説は用意してこなかった
だから俺の番は終わりにして まとめに入らないか
so let's just skip that and continue to the summary.
奉太郎 何か思いついたね
Houtarou, you figured something out, didn't you?
まあな 一通りの説明はつくだろう
I guess. It's one explanation, at least.
何かわかったんですね 折木さん
You figured something out, Oreki?
Calm down, Chitanda.
まあまあ 千反田さん 落ち着いて
Let's hear it.
聞いてあげようじゃないの がっかりさせないでよね
Don't let us all down, now.
Right, let's go through everything in order.
そうだな 順を追って説明しよう
まずは「いつ」
First, when was it?
45 years ago
四十五年前だ 問題は時期だな
45 years ago.
The problem is, what was the time of year?
「氷菓」と「団結と祝砲」の両方を信じると
If we believe both Hyouka and Salute and Solidarity,
Incident
then the incident was in June,
事件が六月で 先輩が去ったのは十月だ
Incident
June
but he left in October.
Expulsion
October
Where?
次に「どこで」
Next, where was it?
At Kamiyama High School.
Kamiyama High School
神山高校でだ
Next, who did it?
で 「誰」が
Who?
「団結と祝砲」から事件の主役は古典部部長関谷純だ
According to Salute and Solidarity,
Sekitani Jun, president of the Classics Club, was at the center of the incident.
Sekitani Jun
神高月報によると 全校生徒も事件に関わっていたのがわかる
And from the Kami High Monthly,
we know that the whole student body was involved.
Why?
Finally, why?
そして 「なぜ」
全校生徒が立ち上がる相手って言ったら
Who would the students have risen up against? The teachers.
まあ 教師陣だな
伊原の言葉を借りれば 立ち上がった理由は「自主性が損なわれて」だ
Their reason was, quoting Ibara, that "their autonomy was threatened".
Autonomy Threatened
そして 事件の原因は
And the reason for the incident was...
the culture fair.
文化祭だ
事件の原因が文化祭だと どこかに書いてありましたっけ？
Did you read that somewhere? That it was the culture fair?
No. To start with the conclusion,
いや 結論から言うと
June
六月に教師陣と生徒側とで話し合いが持たれ
the students negotiated with the teachers in June,
June
October
then the fair was held in October.
十月に文化祭が開催されることになったと 俺は見てる
June
October
By "negotiations",
話し合いって この「文化祭を考える会」のことかい
do you mean this "culture fair discussion meeting"?
そうだ よく見てみろ
Yes. Look at it closely.
Each item has either a circle or a square before it, right?
文の頭に丸と四角のマークがありますね
I get it!
わかった 四角が毎年恒例の行事 丸がその年だけに起きたことでしょ
A square means an event that happens every year, and a circle means this year only!
他の年のも見てみたが それで間違いないだろ
I looked at the other years as well, and that's what I concluded.
なぜ四十五年前にだけ文化祭を考える会が開かれたのか
Now why was there just one "culture fair discussion meeting", 45 years ago?
おそらく 生徒からの強い要求があったからだ
Most likely because there was a strong demand for it from the students.
ヒントは「氷菓」にある
The hint is in Hyouka itself.
ここだ
Right here.
「この一年で先輩は英雄から伝説になった
"The year that he began as a hero and finished as a legend."
"The culture fair was celebrated for five days as always."
文化祭は今年も五日間盛大に行われる」
The point isn't that it was held, but that it lasted five days.
ポイトは「行われる」じゃなく 「五日間」の方にあると思う
What do you mean?
どういうこと？
「五日間」って言うのが英雄関谷純の戦果だってことさ
It means that those five days were the fruit of Sekitani Jun's heroic fight.
これは推測だが この校長の「学力重視」宣言とあわせて考えると
It's just a guess,
but maybe the key is this announcement from the principal about the importance of study.
5 days
校長は平日に五日間もある文化祭を縮小しようとしたんじゃないか
The principal had most likely tried to cut the five days of the culture fair short.
だから 全学があれほど怒りに燃え上がったんだろう
That's why all the students rose up angrily.
これが事件の原因 「なぜ」だ
That's the reason, the "why".
Why?
で 実際の行動 「どのように」
And as for the way they did it, the "how":
How?
Classics Club president Sekitani Jun
古典部部長関谷純君の英雄的指導に支えられた果敢なる実行主義が行われた
"Under the heroic leadership of the Classics Club's president Sekitani Jun,
Heroic Leadership
Daring Activism
our daring activism broke the ranks of the spineless authoritarians."
最後の「なにを」に繋がるな
This leads to the final "what".
What?
生徒たちは暴力は振るわなかった やってもボイコットくらいだろう
The students used no violence.
Violence
I guess they just organized a boycott.
学校側は仕方なく生徒側と話し合い 文化祭縮小を断念した
The school had no choice but to negotiate with the students,
and they gave up on cutting the culture fair short.
But the price they paid was the expulsion of their hero, Sekitani Jun.
だが その代償として 英雄関谷純を退学にした
Incident: June
Why was there a four-month gap between the incident and his expulsion?
Expulsion: October
事件と退学の時期がなんでずれてるか
If they had expelled him right away, that would have caused even more unrest.
関谷純を退学にしたら 騒動はますます大きくなる
だから 熱狂が収まる頃 文化祭の後にしたんじゃないか
That's why they waited until after the culture fair, when things had calmed down.
俺のまとめは以上だ
And that's the end of my summary.
四十五年前 伯父にそんなことが
45 years ago...
That's what happened to my uncle?
I knew I could count on you, Oreki.
さすがです 折木さん
いや なかなかお見事だったよ 奉太郎
That was impressive, Houtarou.
うん なるほどだ
It all makes sense.
Oreki did it again! I can't believe it!
また折木が 信じられない
It's just luck.
たまたまだ
皆さん 質問はありますか
Do you have any questions?
異議なし
No issues here.
悔しいけど 当たってると思う
I hate to admit it, but he's probably right.
では 今の折木さんの説を軸に今年の文集を作っていきましょう
Then, we'll put together an anthology for this year centered around Oreki's theory.
Let's talk about the details later.
詳しい内容はまた後日ですね
それでは解散です お疲れ様でした
This meeting is closed.
Thank you all for your hard work.
本当にありがとうございました
Really, thank you so much.
I didn't do it alone.
俺だけでやったことじゃないさ
No, it was thanks to you.
いいえ 折木さんのお陰です
傘貸してもらってわるいな
Thanks for the umbrella.
じゃ また
See you.
But then...
でも だったら 私はどうして泣いたのでしょうか
Why did I cry?
今夜恋に変わる　幸せな夢で会おう
Let us meet in a blissful dream tonight, let it be our love
きっと　ねぇ見つけてね
Find me, I beg you
まどろみの約束
We promised to meet, drifting in and out of sleep
This sprouting warmth confuses us
芽生えてた温もり　暖かくて戸惑う
Don't you understand this feeling yet?
こんな気持ちをまだ　あなたは分からないよ
そんな視線には意味なんて　別にないはず
Normally such random glances hold no meaning
だって友達にしてるのと同じ
Isn't it the same when making friends?
明け方に消えてく　小さな願星
The little shooting stars we wish upon, vanishing into the dawn
夜の間だけの魔法を…
are a magic that only unfolds in the night
今夜恋に変わる　幸せな夢で会おう
Let us meet in a blissful dream tonight, let it be our love
きっと　ねぇ見つけてね
Find me, I beg you
まどろみの約束
We promised to meet, drifting in and out of sleep
次回 歴史ある古典部の真実
Next time: The Truth of the Classics Club and Its Past.
The Truth of the Classics Club and Its Past